Guide to the Cyril Clemens Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Cyril Clemens papers
1864-1979
YCAL MSS 5
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
The papers contain writings, correspondence, and printed materials about Mark Twain.
Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cyril Clemens, 1969-82.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Beinecke Library also owns a collection of pamphlets by and about Cyril Clemens and books donated and annotated by Clemens. These materials are catalogued separately.
CYRIL CONISTON CLEMENS (1902-)
Cyril Coniston Clemens, son of James Ross and Katherine Boland Clemens and cousin of Mark Twain, was born in St. Louis, Missouri, on July 14, 1902. After attending Canterbury School in New Milford, Connecticut, he continued his education at St. Louis University High School and received his A.B. and M.A. degrees from Washington University (St. Louis). He married Nan B. Shallcross on October 8, 1933. [Selby, P. O. 116 Short Biographies of Persons Associated with Mark Twain, 1970, p.4.]
Clemens founded the International Mark Twain Society in 1930 and edited the Mark Twain Quarterly, which later became the Mark Twain Journal, from 1936-82. His most popular biography, My Cousin Mark Twain, was published in 1939, followed by The Man from Missouri: A Biography of Harry S. Truman in 1945. He also wrote a number of short biographies which were published by the International Mark Twain Society, 1932-70, including sketches of Thomas Hardy, A. E. Housman, George Santayana, and Lytton Strachey.
Scope and Contents
The Cyril Clemens Papers contain writings, photocopies of correspondence, and printed papers about Mark Twain. While the papers span the dates 1864-1979, the bulk of the material covers the years 1927-79.
The papers begin with twelve folders of Clemens's Writings, including the corrected page proof of his most popular title, My Cousin Mark Twain; corrected galleys for two numbers of the International Mark Twain Society's biographical series; and the manuscripts of a review and two articles published in the Overland Monthly.
The rest of the papers are arranged by subject and begin with photocopies of family correspondence and printed papers. These include a May 1864 letter from Orion Clemens, Mark Twain's brother, to T. S. Parvin; and a joint letter from Mark Twain and his wife to Miss Boland, who was to become Cyril Clemens's mother, upon her engagement to James Ross Clemens in 1899. The family printed papers contain biographical information about Clemens.
As president of the International Mark Twain Society, Clemens wrote to many well-known public figures, including Sigmund Freud, Ernest Hemingway, Ogden Nash, Richard M. Nixon, Mohamed Anwar El Sadat, George Bernard Shaw, and William Howard Taft, informing them that they had been elected Knights of Mark Twain by the Society. Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Jimmy Carter, and Robert Frost also received the Mark Twain Medal. Copies of their letters of acceptance and an inscription by Ezra Pound are arranged alphabetically and are followed by printed papers generated by the Society, such as brochures, bookplates, and tear sheets from the Mark Twain Journal.
Clemens also asked famous friends and acquaintances to send him their remembrances of Mark Twain. The last folder contains copies of tributes from Thomas Edison, Lyndon Johnson, Helen Keller, Benito Mussolini, Eugene O'Neill, and Alice B. Toklas; magazine excerpts; and a typescript by P. O. Selby on "The Langdon-Clemens Grave Plot."
Biography; Authors; Biographers; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; International Mark Twain Society
- Writings
  - BOOKS
    - The Man from Missouri: Harry S. Truman: printed half-title, [1945] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mark Twain and Harry S. Truman: corrected galley proofs, [1950] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mark Twain and Lyndon B. Johnson: corrected galley proofs, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mark Twain for Young People: publication agreement, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mark Twain's Jest Book: copyright certificate, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - My Cousin Mark Twain: corrected page proofs, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - SHORTER WORKS
    - "A Chat with Joseph Conrad": Conradiana, 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Mark Twain: [1835-1910]"
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: folder 12
    - [Review of] The Ordeal of Mark Twain by Van Wyck Brooks, 1927 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Some Unpublished Letters by Mark Twain": Overland Monthly, [1929] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Stephen Vincent Benét, 1898-1943", [ca. 1944] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "A Visit to Mark Twain's Country": Overland Monthly Also contains: "Mark Twain: [1835- 1910]": Overland Monthly, [1929] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Other Papers
  - Family
    - Correspondence, 1864-1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Printed papers, 1913-78 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - International Mark Twain Society
    - Correspondence, 1927-79 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Printed papers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mark Twain
    - Correspondence about, 1927-77 (Box 1, Folder 17)